We have a lot of choices
to make about our diet.
Add to that, doing
the right thing
when it comes
to preventing
and treating a
chronic disease,
fighting a virus,
or losing weight,
and suddenly our
nutrition choices
can seem almost
overwhelming.
Well, I’m here to help.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Does it ever seem to you
that some of us are kept from
living longer, healthier lives
because of our skin color?
In our first story,
we look at health equity
and why black Americans
are sicker and die younger
than their white counterparts
on average.
During the COVID-19 pandemic,
the death rate for African Americans
was as much as six times
higher than white America.
The higher Black pandemic deaths
placed a harsh spotlight on their
longstanding higher mortality and
diminished longevity in general.
Unfortunately, diminished
African American life expectancy
predates the COVID-19
pandemic by decades.
The Black-white death gap
for women is about 3 years,
and for men closer to 5 years.
The COVID-19 death disparities
may have to do with limited access
to healthy food in predominantly
Black communities,
the housing density,
the need to work or else,
the inability to practice
social distancing,
but also the underlying
burden of ill health.
Increased COVID-19 mortality and
complications occur more often
in individuals with pre-existing
conditions like hypertension,
obesity, diabetes, and
cardiovascular disease,
comorbidities that are more
prevalent in African Americans.
More high blood pressure,
more diabetes, more strokes,
and more likely to die at early
ages from all causes put together.
The question is why?
Why do Black Americans
live sicker and die younger
than their white counterparts?
Well, one big factor is
socioeconomic status.
In the United States, race
is closely tied to class,
with African Americans about twice
as likely to be living in poverty.
On average, education levels are
lower as well; however, even
among African Americans whose
socioeconomic status is comparable
to that of whites, despite the
higher education and more
socioeconomic resources,
health outcomes are still poorer.
Part of that has to do
with lifestyle behaviors.
For example, fewer than
5% of African American adults
met physical activity guidelines.
Smoking rates are
actually comparable,
though African Americans
tend to be exposed
to more second-hand smoke
and have lower quit rates.
This may be because they're more
likely to use menthol cigarettes,
which enhance the addictive
potential of nicotine.
Why menthol? Because tobacco
companies target the marketing
of mentholated products
to African Americans.
Black lives... Black lung.
Similarly, if you look at food messages
on African American television shows,
not only does Black prime time contain
a greater number of food commercials,
African American audiences may
be receiving nearly 3 times as many
advertisements for low-nutrient
junk such as candy and soda.
That may be one reason why
African Americans tend to consume
fewer fresh fruits and vegetables and
are more likely to eat junkier foods.
Of course, where are you going to get
those fresh fruits and vegetables?
There are fewer supermarkets
located in Black neighborhoods
compared with white neighborhoods,
as in four times fewer supermarkets.
What Black neighborhoods do
excel in though is fast food.
Predominantly Black neighborhoods
have 60% more fast food restaurants
per square mile compared to
predominantly white neighborhoods.
Now, of course, dietary behaviors
alone do not fully explain
the significant differences
in diet-related disease patterns
between racial groups.
There are differences in employment
and poverty and home ownership
and healthcare access, all of
which can affect outcomes.
But while there are certainly many
social and economic factors such as
racism and income inequality that
contribute to health disparities,
there is good evidence that simply
eating a more plant-based diet
could help eliminate disparities in
cardiovascular disease and diabetes.
Here's the diabetes data.
Even after controlling for education,
income, physical activity,
and even BMI, non-Blacks
eating strictly plant-based diets
had 57% lower odds of diabetes,
and among Black vegans, it was
even more striking, 70% lower odds.
And that was after
taking BMI into account.
So even at the same weight,
Black vegans had 70% lower odds
of diabetes than Black omnivores.
And the racial disparity is
only about half that, 36%.
So the increased risk of diabetes
among Black participants
was on the order of one-third,
while the protection afforded
by vegan diets in this
subgroup was about 70%.
Even just a vegetarian diet that
includes still eating dairy and eggs
may more than counteract the
racial disparity in diabetes risk.
And they're not the same weight.
African Americans have higher
obesity rates, cutting their
life spans by six years.
But Black vegetarians and
vegans have less than half
the risk of obesity, compared
to those who eat meat,
and this is after adjusting for
differences in physical activity.
So even at the same exercise levels,
those eating more plant based
had but a fraction
of the obesity risk.
High blood pressure.
In African Americans, hypertension
is the most significant contributor
to their increased cardiovascular
disease burden and mortality.
But Black vegetarians and vegans
combined had 44% lower odds
of hypertension, an important
finding for Black individuals
where hypertension is so prevalent,
with no benefit found for those
who cut out all other meat,
but continued to eat fish.
And the same thing found for total
cholesterol and LDL cholesterol:
cutting odds in half among
Black vegetarians and vegans.
As with non-Blacks,
the researchers conclude,
"these results suggest that
there are sizeable advantages
to a vegetarian diet
in Black individuals."
What about vegetarians
versus vegans?
The title gives it all away:
"Cardiovascular Disease
Risk Factors are Even Lower
in African American Vegans..."
This is something we've
known about when
Caucasian vegans have been
compared to vegetarians.
However, it was not known
whether African American vegans
exhibited a more favorable
cholesterol profile until now.
Significantly lower LDL
cholesterol in vegans.
Now, of course, the vegans
were also significantly slimmer:
on average normal weight as opposed
to the over-weight vegetarians.
But even after taking
that into account,
those eating more plant based
had significantly lower cholesterol.
So there's tremendous
potential for plant-based diets
to promote health among Blacks
living in the United States.
In fact, they may have
an even greater benefit.
For example, African Americans
have an excess burden
of chronic kidney disease, not
only because they have more
high blood pressure and diabetes,
but there are genetic factors:
8% to 12% of African Americans
are carriers of the sickle cell trait,
which places them at significantly
higher risk of kidney disease.
So while Blacks represent a relatively
small fraction of the US population,
they account for more than a
third of all patients on dialysis
due to chronic kidney disease.
And that's where plant-based diets
can come in: shown to protect
against both chronic kidney disease
development as well as progression.
Three-quarters of Blacks
are lactose intolerant, too,
so would again stand to benefit
even more from eating plant based.
It is unacceptable that for decades,
the American healthcare system
has failed African Americans and
other minority communities
in terms of helping to prevent
some of our leading killers.
But that just makes it all
the more important for them
to take the reins of
their own health destiny.
In our next story, we look at what role
diet and baby powder may play
in the development of fibroids
and ovarian cancer.
If you randomly select a group of women
and ultrasound their uterus,
the majority of them have
fibroid tumors by age 50,
and by most, I mean, more
than 80% of black women,
and about nearly 70% of white women.
Half of white women already have fibroids
by their early 40s,
and the same could be said
for African-American
women in their mid 30s.
After getting over the shock
of how widespread fibroids are,
the next question becomes,
why the racial disparity.
Is it diet, stress,
environmental exposures?
Maybe whatever it is
could offer a clue
as to what causes fibroids.
For example, African-Americans
tend to have
a lower intake of
fruits and vegetables,
and fruits and vegetables
appear protective
against fibroids,
particularly citrus,
though not apparently
just citrus juice.
It’s interesting, if you measure
the levels of beta-carotene
in fresh surgical tissue
samples of uterine fibroids
and adjacent normal
uterus tissue
obtained during hysterectomies,
you find significantly lower
concentrations in the fibroids.
In fact, beta-carotene
was not even detectable
in half the
fibroid specimens.
The same thing is actually
found in cancer.
Most cancerous tissues tested
had undetectable levels of beta carotene,
compared to the normal tissue
right next to the tumor.
So, maybe decreased
levels of beta-carotene
somehow plays a role in
causing these conditions?
Sounds like a bit of a stretch,
but you don’t know...
until you put
it to the test.
But, there had never been a
randomized controlled clinical trial
of fruits and vegetables for fibroids..
until, never.
They did do a randomized
controlled trial
of kind-of-a-fruit-and-vegetable-
at-the-same-time—tomatoes—
but for the prevention of
fibroids in Japanese quail,
and most of my patients are
not Japanese, nor quail.
The action of lycopene,
the red pigment in tomatoes,
“in an animal model may
not accurately represent
lycopene action in humans.”
And indeed, the Harvard
Nurse’s study found
no apparent link between lycopene
consumption and fibroids.
So, yeah, fruits and at
least green vegetables
may have a protective effect,
but we won’t know for sure until
they’re properly
put to the test.
Vitamin D is another possibility
as to why African-Americans
disproportionately
suffer from fibroids.
Women with darker
skin are more likely
to be Vitamin D deficient;
as many as 80% of black women
may have inadequate levels of Vitamin D,
compared to only
1 in 5 white women.
Vitamin D does inhibit
fibroid cell proliferation—
in a petri dish.
It may be able to shrink
tumors in your pet rat,
but what about people?
A population study did find that women
with sufficient vitamin D levels
in their blood had about a
third lower odds of fibroids,
consistent with the finding that women
who report lots of sun exposure
also appear to be protected,
but until there’s
an interventional trial
where women are randomized
to vitamin D or placebo,
we won’t know for
sure if vitamin D
plays a role in fibroid prevention
or treatment or not.
African-American women
are also more likely
to sprinkle baby powder
on their genitals,
which may not only
double the odds of fibroids
but may increase the
risk of ovarian cancer,
the deadliest gynecological cancer.
Internal memos show
Johnson & Johnson knew
about the cancer risk,
but still decided
to target African-Americans.
“Think of us”,
Johnson & Johnson said,
“as a lifetime friend
of the family,”
a lifetime cut short, perhaps,
by its baby powder,
or at least so said a jury,
which recently awarded a family
$110 million in damages.
On top of the $200 million
in verdicts from last year,
with thousands of
lawsuits pending
after internal memos
revealed that decades ago,
their own contracted toxicologists
were warning the company that
there are multiple studies
showing a cancer link,
and anyone who denies this risk
will be perceived by the
public in the same light
as those who denied a link
between smoking cigarettes and cancer:
“Denying the obvious, in the face
of all evidence to the contrary.”
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a vital, timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my latest book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
Or go to your local public
library for that matter.
For recipes, check out
my new “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books
goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.